Guide to the William C. Marshall Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
William Crosby Marshall papers
1893-1908
MS 983
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
The bulk of the papers consists of two textbooks and a notebook on the construction of ships dating from his enrollment in the École d'Application du Gènie Maritime in Paris, 1906-1907. Also included are later notebooks and drawings on engineering projects. Also in the papers is a commonplace book kept by Harriette N. Marshall.
Marshall, William Crosby, 1870-1934
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1941.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of these papers of William Crosby Marshall date from his study at the École d'Application du Gènie Maritime in Paris, 1906-1907. There are two textbooks in French and a notebook on the construction of ships. Other papers include two further notebooks on engineering subjects kept while Marshall was working in the United States, and various geometrical drawings. Finally, these papers are accompanied by a commonplace book kept by Harriette N. Marshall in the 1890s. A number of newspaper clippings and other loose papers are laid in. Harriette Marshall's relationship to William Marshall is not known.
Biographical / Historical
William Crosby Marshall, Ph.B. 1890.
Born September 21, 1870, in Avon, Conn.
Died February 1, 1934, in Wallingford, Conn.
Father, Rev. Henry Grimes Marshall, '60. Mother, Marietta (Crosby) Marshall. Yale relatives include two nephews: Henry C. Marshall, '30, and Charles E. Marshall, '32.
Structural engineer with Berlin Iron Bridge Company 1890-93; graduate student in Sheffield Scientific School 1893-94 (M.E. 1894); assistant in mechanical engineering at Yale 1894-96; instructor in drawing and descriptive geometry 1896-1902; assistant professor 1902-1912 and in machine design (1912-13); graduate student Sheffield Scientific School 1895-1900 (C.E. 1900); studied at École des Beaux Arts and École du Gènie Maritime, Paris, 1905-07; consulting engineer to Federal Sugar Refining Company 1913-15; mechanical engineer with Remington Arms Union Metallic Cartridge Company, of Bridgeport, Conn., 1915-17; mechanical engineer with Holt Manufacturing Company, Peoria, Ill., in 1917; commissioned as a Captain in Ordnance Department, U.S.A., September 13, 1917; assistant chief of Inspection Division, Small Arms Weapons Section, at Washington, D.C., until given his discharge February 19, 1919; trade commissioner for U.S. Department of Commerce on industrial machinery in Italy February-September, 1919; mechanical engineer with National Spun Silk Company, New York, 1919-1920; consulting engineer in New York, 1920-1921; consulting engineer in New York 1920-1921; chief engineer with U.S. Hoffman Machinery Company of Syracuse, N.Y., 1921-22; mechanical engineer with Trexler Company of America at Wilmington, Del., 1922-23; maintenance and plant engineer with Richard Hellman, Inc., at Long Island City, N.Y., 1923-24; manager of Graduate Placement Bureau at New York Yale Club 1924-25; associate editor of Engineering Index, service magazine of American Society of Mechanical Engineers, 1927-29; had since lived in Milford, Conn.; town plan and building inspector since 1930; member American Society of Mechanical Engineers, Society of Automotive Engineers, Society for the Promotion of Engineering Education, Yale Engineering Association, Sigma Xi (elected to Yale chapter during 1895-96), and Congregational church, in Cromwell, Conn., and later in New Haven.
Married (1) March 24, 1896, in Cromwell, Anna Hall, daughter of Edward Stevens and Elizabeth Strickland (Savage) Coe. Mr. and Mrs. Marshall were divorced in 1919. Married (2) November 3, 1927, in New York City, Genevieve Holbrook, daughter of William Fowler and Carolyn May (Holbrook) Adams. One son, John Crosby.
Death due to acute miliary tuberculosis. Buried in Milford (Conn.) Cemetery. Survived by wife, son, stepmother, and a half brother, Dr. Samuel A. Marshall, '98.
[Taken from Yale Obituary Record, 1931-34, pages 156-7.]
Americans -- France; Engineering; Shipbuilding; Shipping; France; Commonplace books; Engineers; Marshall, Harriette N.; Marshall, William Crosby, 1870-1934; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - William Crosby Marshall
    - Cours de Construction du navire, 2 vols., by M. Rougé, 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 1 - 2)
    - Cours de Machines à Vapeur, by M. Lelong, 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Notebooks
      - "Triple Expansion Engine", 1893 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - "Construction des Navires", 1906 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - "Yacht Design", 1908 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Geometrical drawings, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Harriette N. Marshall: commonplace book, [1890s] (Box 2, Folder 8)